RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In our very first example,
we imagine an urn with 5 beads--
3 blue, 2 red.
To review, to compute the probability distribution of 1 draw,
we simply listed out all the possibilities-- there were 5--
and then for each event, we counted how many of these possibilities
were associated with that event.
So for example, for the blue beads the probability is 0.6.
For more complicated examples, however, these computations
are not necessarily straightforward.
For example, what does the probability that if I
draw 5 cards without replacement, I get all cards
of the same suit, what is called a flush in poker?
Discrete probability teaches us how to make
these computations using mathematics.
Here we focus on how to use R code.
So we&#39;re going to use card games as examples.
So let&#39;s start by constructing a deck of cards
using R. For this, we will use the function expand.grid and the function
Paste.
We use Paste to create strings by joining smaller strings.
For example, if we have the number and the suit for a card,
in 2 different variables we can create the card name using Paste like this.
It also works on pairs of vectors.
It performs the operation element-wise.
So if we type this line of code, we get the following result.
The function expand.grid gives us all the combinations of 2 lists.
So for example, if you have blue and black pants
and white, gray, and plaid shirt, all your combinations
can be computed using the expand.grid function like this.
You can see all 6 combinations.
So here&#39;s how we generate a deck of cards.
We define the four suits, we define the 13 numbers,
and then we create the deck using expand.grid and then pasting together
the 2 columns that expand.grid creates.
Now that we have a deck constructed, we can now start answering questions
about probability.
Let&#39;s start by doing something simple.
Let&#39;s double-check that the probability of a king in the first card is 1 in 13.
We simply compute the proportion of possible outcomes
that satisfy our condition.
So we create a vector that contains the four ways we can get a king.
That&#39;s going to be the kings variable.
And then we simply check what proportion of the deck is one of these cards
and we get the answer that we expect--
0.076 dot dot dot, which is 1 in 13.
Now, how about the conditional probability of the second card being a king,
given that the first was a king?
Earlier we deduced that if 1 king is already out, then there&#39;s 51 left.
So the probability is 3 in 51.
But let&#39;s confirm by listing out all possible outcomes.
To do this, we&#39;re going to use the combinations and permutations
functions that are available from the gtools package.
The permutations function computes for any list of size n
all the different ways we can select R items.
So here&#39;s an example--
here all the ways we can choose 2 numbers from the list 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
Notice that the order matters.
So 3, 1 is different than 1, 3, So it appears in our permutations.
Also notice that 1, 1; 2, 2; and 3, 3 don&#39;t
appear, because once we pick a number, it can&#39;t appear again.
Optionally for this function permutations, we can add a vector.
So for example, if you want to see 5 random 7-digit phone numbers out
of all possible phone numbers, you could type code like this.
Here we&#39;re defining a vector of digits that goes from 0 to 9 rather than 1
through 10.
So these four lines of code generate all phone numbers, picks 5 at random,
and then shows them to you.
To compute all possible ways that we can choose 2 cards when the order matters,
we simply type the following piece of code.
Here we use permutations.
There&#39;s 52 cards, we&#39;re going to choose 2,
and we&#39;re going to select them out of the vector that includes our card
names, which we called deck earlier.
This is going to be a matrix with 2 dimensions, 2 columns,
and in this case, it&#39;s going to have 2,652 rows.
Those are all the permutations.
Now, we&#39;re going to define the first card and the second card
by grabbing the first and second columns using this simple piece of code.
And now we can, for example, check how many cases
have a first card that is a king--
that&#39;s 204.
And now to find the conditional probability,
we ask what fraction of these 204 have also a king in the second card.
So this case we type the following piece of code.
We add all the cases that have king in the first, king in the second,
and divide by the cases that have a king in the first.
And now we get the answer 0.058 dot dot dot, which is exactly 3 out of 51,
which we had already deduced.
Note that the code we just saw is equivalent to this piece of code
where we compute the proportions instead of the totals.
And this also gives us the answer that we want, 3 out
of 51. This is an R version of the multiplication rule, which tells us
the probability of B, given A, is equal to proportion of A and B,
or the probability of A and B, divided by the proportion of A
or the probability of A.
Now, what if the order does not matter?
For example, in blackjack, if you get an ace and a face card or a 10,
it&#39;s called a natural 21, and you win automatically.
If we want to compute the probability of this happening,
we want to enumerate the combinations, not permutations,
since the order doesn&#39;t matter.
So if we get an A and a king, king and an A, it&#39;s still a 21.
We don&#39;t want to count that twice.
So notice the difference between the permutations functions, which
lists all permutations, and the combination function,
where order does not matter.
This means that 2, 1 doesn&#39;t appear because 1, 2 already appeared.
Similarly, 3, 1 and 3, 2 don&#39;t appear.
So to compute the probability of a natural 21 in blackjack,
we can do this.
We can define a vector that includes all the aces, a vector that
includes all the face cards, then we generate
all the combinations of picking 2 cards out of 52, and then we simply count.
How often do we get aces and a face card?
And we get the answer 0.048 dot, dot, dot.
Now, notice that in the previous piece of code
we assumed that the aces come first.
This is only because we know the way that combination
generates and enumerates possibilities.
But if we want to be safe, we can instead
type this code, which considers both possibilities.
We get the same answer, and again, this is
because we know how combinations works and how it lists the possibilities.
Instead of using combinations to deduce the exact probability of a natural 21,
we can also use a Monte Carlo to estimate this probability.
In this case, we draw two cards over and over
and keep track of how many 21&#39;s we get.
We can use the function sample to draw a card without a replacement like this.
Here&#39;s 1 hand.
We didn&#39;t get a 21 there.
And then check if 1 card is an ace and the other is a face card or a 10.
Now we simply repeat this over and over and we get a very good approximation--
in this case, 0.0488.