RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Suppose you&#39;re in a classroom with 50 people.
If we assume this is a randomly selected group,
what is the chance that at least two people have the same birthday?
Although it is somewhat advanced, we can actually deduce this mathematically,
and we do this later, but now, we&#39;re going to use Monte Carlo simulations.
For simplicity, we assumed that nobody was born on February 29th.
This actually doesn&#39;t change the answer much.
All right, first, note that birthdays can be represented
as numbers between 1 and 365.
So a sample of 50 random birthdays can be obtained simply
using the sample function, like this.
To check if, in this particular set of 50 people we have at least two
with the same birthday, we can use the function duplicated,
which returns true whenever an element of a vector
has already appeared in that vector.
So here&#39;s an example.
If I type duplicated 1, 2, 3, 1, 4, 3, 5, ,
we get true&#39;s for the 1 and the 3 the second time they appear.
So to check if two birthdays were the same,
we simply use any and duplicated functions, like this.
And in the case that we just generated, we actually do have this happening.
We did have two people, at least two people, with the same birthday.
We get true.
Now, to estimate the probability, we&#39;re going to repeat this experiment.
We&#39;re going to run a Monte Carlo simulation over and over again.
So what we do is we do it 10,000 times.
We use the replicate function like this.
And when we&#39;re done, we get that the probability
of having two people, at least two people, with the same birthday
in a group of 50 people is about 98%.
Were you expecting this to be so high?
People tend to underestimate these probabilities,
so it might be an opportunity for you to bet and make
some money off of your friends.
To get an intuition as to why this is so high,
think of what happens as you get close to 365 people.
At this stage, we run out of days, and the probability is 1.
In the next video, we&#39;re going to actually compute
this probability for different group sizes
and see how fast it gets close to 1.