RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Say you want to use what you&#39;ve just
learned about the birthday problem to bet
with friends about two people having the same birthday in a group of people.
When are the chances larger than 50%?
Larger than 75%?
Let&#39;s create a lookup table.
We can quickly create a function to compute this for any group.
We write the function like this.
We&#39;ll call it compute prob, and we&#39;ll basically
make the calculations for the probability
of two people having the same birthday.
We will use a small Monte Carlo simulation to do it.
Now that we&#39;ve done this, we want to compute this function,
we want to apply this function to several values of n,
let&#39;s say from 1 to 60.
Let&#39;s define n as a sequence starting at 1 and ending at 60.
Now, we can use a for loop to apply this function to each value in n,
but it turns out that for loops are rarely the preferred approach in R.
In general, we try to perform operations on entire vectors.
Arithmetic operations, for example, operate
on vectors in an element wise fashion.
We saw this when we learned about R. So if we type x equals 1 through 10,
now X is the vector starting at 1 and ending at 10,
and we compute the square root of x, it actually
computes the square root for each element.
Equally, if we define y to be 1 through 10, and then multiply x by y,
it multiplies each element 1 by 1--
1 times 1, 2 times 2, et cetera.
So there&#39;s really no need for for loops.
But not all functions work this way.
You can&#39;t just send a vector to any function in R.
For example, the function we just wrote does not work element-wise
since it&#39;s expecting a scalar, it&#39;s expecting an n.
This piece of code does not do what we want.
If we type compute prob and send it the vector n, we will not get what we want.
We will get just one number.
What we can do instead is use the function sapply.
sapply permits us to perform element-wise operations
on any function.
Here&#39;s how it works.
We&#39;ll define a simple example for the vector 1 through 10.
If we want to apply the square roots of each element of x,
we can simply type sapply x comma square root,
and it&#39;ll apply square root to each element of x.
Of course, we don&#39;t need to do this because square root already does that,
but we are using it as a simple example.
So for our case, we can simply type prob equals sapply n-- n is our vector--
and then the function we define compute prob.
And this will assign to each element of prob
the probability of two people having the same birthday for that n.
And now we can very quickly make a plot.
We plot the probability of two people having the same birthday
against the size of the group.
Now, let&#39;s compute the exact probabilities
rather than use Monte Carlo simulations.
The function we just defined uses a Monte Carlo simulation,
but we can use what we&#39;ve learned about probability theory
to compute the exact value.
Not only do we get the exact answer using math,
but the computations are much faster since we
don&#39;t have to generate experiments.
We simply get a number.
To make the math simpler for this particular problem,
instead of computing the probability of it happening,
we&#39;ll compute the probability of it not happening,
and then we can use the multiplication rule.
Let&#39;s start with the first person.
The probability that person 1 has a unique birthday is 1, of course.
All right.
Now let&#39;s move on to the second one.
The probability that the second person has
a unique birthday given that person 1 already took one of the days
is 364 divided by 365.
Then for a person 3, given that the first two people already
have unique birthdays, that leaves 363.
So now that probability is 363 divided by 365.
If we continue this way and find the chances of all,
say, 50 people having unique birthdays, we would multiply 1 times 364 divided
by 365, times 363 divided by 365, dot dot
dot, all the way to the 50th element.
Here&#39;s the equation.
Now, we can easily write a function that does this.
This time we&#39;ll call it exact prob.
It takes n as a argument, and it computes
this probability using this simple code.
Now we can compute each probability for each n using sapply again, like this.
And if we plot it, we can see that the Monte Carlo
simulations were almost exactly right.
They were almost exact approximations of the actual value.
Now, notice had it not been possible to compute
the exact probabilities, something that sometimes happens,
we would have still been able to accurately estimate
the probabilities using Monte Carlo.