RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In the examples we have seen,
we have used 10,000 Monte Carlo experiments.
It turns out that this provided very accurate estimates for the examples
we looked at.
In more complex calculations, 10,000 may not nearly be enough.
Also for some calculations, 10,000 experiments
might not be computationally feasible, and it might be more than we need.
In practice, we won&#39;t know what the answer
is, so we don&#39;t know if our Monte Carlo estimate is accurate.
We know that the larger the number of experiments, we&#39;ve
been using the letter B to represent that, the better the approximation.
But how big do we need it to be?
This is actually a challenging question, and answering it often requires
advanced theoretical statistics training.
One practical approach we will describe here
is to check for the stability of the estimate.
Here&#39;s an example with the birthday problem.
We&#39;re going to use n equals 22.
There&#39;s 22 people.
So we&#39;re going to run a simulation where we compute or estimate
the probability of two people having a certain birthday using different sizes
of the Monte Carlo simulations.
So the value of b going to go from 10, to 20, to 40, to 100, et cetera.
We compute the simulation, and now we look at the values
that we get for each simulation.
Remember, each simulation has a different b,
a different number of experiments.
When we see this graph, we can see that it&#39;s wiggling up and down.
That&#39;s because the estimate is not stable yet.
It&#39;s not such a great estimate.
But as b gets bigger and bigger, eventually it starts to stabilize.
And that&#39;s when we start getting a feeling for the fact
that now perhaps we have a large enough number of experiments.