RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Taking an opinion poll is being modeled
as taking a random sample from an urn.
We are proposing the use of the proportion of blue beads in our sample
as an estimate of the parameter p.
Once we have this estimate, we can easily
report an estimate of the spread, 2p minus 1.
But for simplicity, we will illustrate the concept of statistical inference
for estimating p.
We will use our knowledge of probability to defend our use of the sample
proportion, and quantify how close we think
it is from the population proportion p.
We start by defining the random variable X. X is
going to be 1 if we pick a blue bead at random, and 0 if it's red.
This implies that we're assuming that the population, the beads in the urn,
are a list of 0s and 1s.
If we sample N beads, then the average of the draws X_1 through X_N
is equivalent to the proportion of blue beads in our sample.
This is because adding the Xs is equivalent to counting the blue beads,
and dividing by the total N turns this into a proportion.
We use the symbol X-bar to represent this average.
In general, in statistics textbooks, a bar on top of a symbol
means the average.
The theory we just learned about the sum of draws
becomes useful, because we know the distribution of the sum N times X-bar.
We know the distribution of the average X-bar,
because N is a non random constant.
For simplicity, let's assume that the draws are independent.
After we see each sample bead, we return it to the urn.
It's a sample with replacement.
In this case, what do we know about the distribution of the sum of draws?
First, we know that the expected value of the sum of draws
is N times the average of the values in the urn.
We know that the average of the 0s and 1s in the urn
must be the proportion p, the value we want to estimate.
Here, we encounter an important difference
with what we did in the probability module.
We don't know what is in the urn.
We know there are blue and red beads, but we don't know how many of each.
This is what we're trying to find out.
We're trying to estimate p.
Just like we use variables to define unknowns in systems of equations,
in statistical inference, we define parameters
to define unknown parts of our models.
In the urn model we are using to mimic an opinion poll,
we do not know the proportion of blue beads in the urn.
We define the parameter p to represent this quantity.
We are going to estimate this parameter.
Note that the ideas presented here, on how we estimate parameters
and provide insights into how good these estimates are,
extrapolate to many data science tasks.
For example, we may ask, what is the difference
in health improvement between patients receiving treatment and a control
group?
We may ask, what are the health effects of smoking on a population?
What are the differences in racial groups of fatal shootings by police?
What is the rate of change in life expectancy in the US during the last 10
years?
All these questions can be framed as a task of estimating
a parameter from a sample.