RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Here we introduce a new motivating problem.
It is an artificial one, but it&#39;ll help us illustrate the concepts needed
to understand distributions.
Later, we&#39;ll move on to more realistic examples.
Pretend that we have to describe the heights of our classmates
to ET, an extraterrestrial that has never seen humans.
As a first step, we need to collect data.
To do this, we asked students to report their heights in inches.
We asked them to provide sex information because we
know there are two different groups of heights, males and females.
We collect the data and save it in a data frame.
We&#39;ve done that already, and here are the first six entries.
One way to convey the heights to ET is to simply
send him the list of 924 heights.
But there are much more effective ways to convey this information,
and understanding the concepts of distributions will help.
To simplify the explanation at first, we focus on male heights.
The most basic statistical summary of a list of objects or numbers
is its distribution.
The simplest way to think of a distribution
is as a compact description of a list with many elements.
This concept should not be new for most of us.
For example, with categorical data, the distribution
simply describes the proportions of each unique category.
For example, the sex represented in the heights data set
can be summarized by the proportions of each of the two categories,
female and male.
This two category frequency table is the simplest form
of a distribution we can form.
Now, we don&#39;t really need to visualize it
since one number describes everything we need to know about this data set.
23% are females and the rest are males.
That&#39;s all we need to know.
When there are more categories, then a simple bar plot
describes the distribution.
Here&#39;s an example showing the proportions of state regions
for the 50 states, plus DC, that we looked at earlier.
We can see in the plot with the height of the bar
tells us the proportion of the four regions
Northeast, South, North Central, and West.
Although this particular plot, a graphical representation of a frequency
table, does not provide much more insights than the table itself,
it is a first example of how we convert a vector
into a visualization that succinctly summarizes
all the information in that vector.
When the data is numerical, the task is much more challenging.
Why is it more complicated?
Well, in general, when data is not categorical,
reporting the frequency of each unique entry
is not an effective summary since most entries are unique.
For example, while several students reported a height of 68 inches,
only one student reported a height of 68.503937007874 inches.
And only one student reported a height of 68.8976377952756 inches.
We assume that they converted from 174 centimeters and 175 centimeters
to inches respectively.
Statistics textbooks teach us that a more useful way
to define a distribution for numerical data
is to define a function that reports the proportion of the data
below a value A for all possible values of A.
This function is called a cumulative distribution function or CDF.
In statistical textbooks, the following mathematical notation is used.
We define a function f of a and make that equal to the proportion of values
x less than or equal to a, which is represented with this Pr, meaning
proportion or probability, and then in parentheses
the event that we require, x less than a.
Here&#39;s a plot of the function f for the height data.
Like the frequency table does for categorical data,
the CDF defines the distribution for numerical data.
From the plot we can see, for example, that 14% of the students in our class
have heights below 66 inches.
How do we know this?
Because if we look at the value of f at 66, it&#39;s .138.
We also see that 84% of our students have heights below 72 inches.
This is because if we look at the value of f at 72, it&#39;s 0.839.
In fact, we can report the proportion of values between any two heights,
say a and b, by computing f of b, and then subtracting f of a.
This means that if we send this plot to ET,
he will have all the information needed to construct the entire list.
Final note, because CDFs can be determined mathematically,
as opposed to using data as we do here, the word empirical
is added to distinguish, and we use the term empirical CDF or ECDF.
Although the CDF provides all the information we need and it is widely
discussed in statistics textbooks, the plot
is actually not very popular in practice.
The main reason is that it does not easily
convey characteristics of interest, such as,
at what value is the distribution centered,
is the distribution symmetric, what range contains 95% of the data.
We can decipher all this from the plot, but it&#39;s not that easy.
Histograms are much preferred because they greatly
facilitate answering such questions.
Histograms sacrifice just a bit of information
to produce plots that are much easier to interpret.
The simplest way to make a histogram is to divide a span of our data
into non-overlapping bins of the same size.
Then for each bin, we count the number of values that fall in that interval.
The histogram plots these counts as bars with the base of the bar the interval.
Here&#39;s a histogram for the height data where we split the range of values
into one inch intervals.
So we start with the interval 53.5 to 54.5,
then divide the rest into one inch intervals,
all the way up to 80.5 to 81.5.
If we send this plot to ET, he will immediately
learn some important properties about our data.
First, the range of data is from 55 to 81,
but perhaps more importantly, he learns that the majority, with more than 95%,
are between 63 and 75 inches.
Second, the heights are close to symmetric around 69 inches.
Also note, that by adding up counts, ET could
obtain very good approximations of the proportion of the data in any interval.
So it provides almost all the information
that we provided with the CDF.
We provide almost all the information contained
in the raw data that is 708 heights, with just 23 bin counts.
So why is it an approximation?
What information do we lose?
Note that all values in each interval are treated as the same
when computing the bin heights.
So for example, the histogram does not distinguish
between 64, 64.1, and 64.2 inches.
Given that these differences are almost unnoticeable to the eye,
in this particular case, the practical implications are negligible.