RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Smooth density plots are similar to histograms,
but are aesthetically more appealing.
Here&#39;s what a smooth density plot looks like for our male heights data.
We&#39;re going to learn how to make these plots and what they mean.
Note that we no longer have sharp edges at the interval boundaries
and that many of the local peaks have been removed.
Also notice that the scale of the y-axis changed from counts to something
new called density.
To understand the smooth densities, we have
to understand estimates, a topic we don&#39;t cover until later.
However, we provide a heuristic explanation
to help you understand the basics, and so you
can use this useful data visualization tool and learn how to interpret it.
The main new concept you have to understand
is that we assume that our list of observed values of observed heights
comes from a much, much larger list of unobserved values.
So in the case of male heights, you can imagine
our lists of students heights comes from a hypothetical list containing
all the heights of all the male students in all the world measured
very precisely.
So as an example, let&#39;s suppose that we have a million of these.
This list of values, like any other list of values, has a distribution.
And this is really what we want to report
to ET, since it is much more general.
Unfortunately, we don&#39;t get to see it.
However, we can make an assumption that helps us perhaps approximate.
Because we&#39;re assuming that we have a million values measured very precisely,
we can make a histogram with very, very small bins.
This is going to help us understand what smooth densities are.
The assumption is that if we do this, consecutive bins will be similar.
This is what we mean by smooth.
We don&#39;t have big jumps from bin to bin.
Here&#39;s a hypothetical histogram with a bin size of 1
from the hypothetical list of 1 million values.
And here&#39;s what happens when we make the bins smaller and smaller.
You can see that the edges start disappearing and the histogram
becomes smoother.
For this hypothetical situation, the smooth density
is basically the curve that goes through the top of the histogram bars
when the bins are very, very small.
You can see it in the plot as a blue curve.
To make the curve not depend on the hypothetical size
of the hypothetical list, we compute the curve on the frequency scale
rather than the count scale.
OK.
Now back to reality.
With our example, we don&#39;t have millions of measurements.
Instead, we have 708 and we can&#39;t make a histogram with very, very small bins.
So how can we estimate this hypothetical smooth curve
that we would see if we would see all the measurements?
So what we&#39;re going to do is we&#39;re going to start
by making a histogram with our data, compute frequencies rather than counts,
and using the bin size appropriate for our data,
so the histogram looks like this.
Because it is a small sample, we get unsmooth variation in these heights.
To smooth the histogram what we&#39;re going to do
is we&#39;re going to start by keeping the heights of the histogram bar shown here
with little points.
We keep these points.
And now we draw a smooth curve that goes through the top
of these histograms bars.
That&#39;s the blue curve.
And we get what we call the smooth density.
Here&#39;s what the final product looks like.
Before we continue, note that smooth is a relative term.
We can actually control the smoothness of the curve that
defines a smooth density through an option in the function, the GG plot
option that computes the smooth density.
Here are two example using different degrees
of smoothness on the same histogram.
On the left, we see a curve this more jagged.
It goes up and down quickly.
And on the right, we see a curve that goes up and then goes down smoothly.
We need to make this choice with care, as the resulting visualization
can change our interpretation of the data.
We should select a degree of smoothness that we
can defend as being representative of the underlying data.
In the case of height, we really do have reason
to believe that there are a proportion of people
with similar heights should be about the same.
For example, the proportion that is 72 inches
should be more similar to the proportion of the 71 inches
than the proportion that is 78 or 65.
This implies that the curve should be pretty smooth, more
like the example on the right than the example on the left.
Always keep in mind that while the histogram is an assumption
free summary, the smooth density is based on assumptions and choices
that you make as a data analyst.
Finally, to be able to interpret density plots,
we need to understand the units of the y-axis.
We point out that interpreting the y-axis of a smooth density plot
is not straightforward.
It is scaled so that the area under the density curve adds up to 1.
So if you imagine, you form a bin with a base that is 1 unit long.
The y-axis value tells us the proportion of values in that bin.
But this is only true if the bin is of size 1.
For other size intervals, the best way to determine the proportion of data
in that interval is by computing the proportion of the total area contained
in that interval.
Here&#39;s an example, if we take the proportion of values between 65 and 68,
it&#39;ll equal the proportion of the graph that is in that blue region
that we&#39;re showing you right there.
The proportion of this area is about 0.31, meaning that about 31%
of our values are between 65 and 68 inches.
Now that we understand this, we are ready to use a smooth density
as a summary.
For this dataset, we would feel quite comfortable
with the smoothness assumption.
And therefore, we&#39;re sharing the aesthetically pleasing figure
with ET, which you could use to understand our male height data.
As a final note, we point out that an advantage
of smooth densities over histograms is that it makes it easier
to compare two distributions.
This is in large part because the jagged edges of the histogram add clutter,
so when we&#39;re comparing two histograms, it makes it a little bit hard to see.
Here&#39;s an example of what it looks like when you use density plots.
With the right argument, GG plot automatically
shades the intersecting regions with different colors.
So it makes it very easy to get an idea of what the two distributions are.