RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Histogram and density plots
provide excellent summaries of a distribution.
But can we summarize even further?
We often see the average and the standard deviation
used as a summary statistic for a list of numbers, a two number summary.
To understand what these summaries are and why they are so widely used,
we need to understand the normal distribution.
The normal distribution, also known as the bell curve
and as the Gaussian distribution, is one of the most famous
mathematical concepts in history.
A reason for this is that approximately normal distributions
occur in many situations.
Examples include, gambling winnings, heights, weights, blood pressure,
standardized test scores, and experimental measurement error.
There are explanations for this, but we explain it later.
Here we focus on how the normal distribution helps us summarize data.
Rather than using data, the normal distribution
is defined with a mathematical formula.
Let&#39;s see what this is.
For any interval, a and b, the proportion of values in the interval
can be computed using this formula.
You don&#39;t need to memorize or understand the details of the formula.
We&#39;re going to have R code that computes it for us.
But note that it is completely defined by just 2 parameters, m and s.
The rest of the symbols in the formula represent the interval ends, a and b,
and known mathematical constants, pi and e.
These two parameters, m and s, are referred to as the average, also
call the mean, that&#39;s why we use the letter m,
and the standard deviation of the distribution respectively.
The distribution is symmetric, centered at the average,
and most values, about 95%, are within two standard deviations
from the average.
Here&#39;s what the distribution looks like when the average is zero
and the standard deviation is one.
The fact that the distribution is defined by just two parameters
implies that if a dataset is approximated by a normal distribution,
all information needed to describe this distribution
can be encoded in just two numbers, the average and the standard deviation,
which we now define for an arbitrary list of numbers.
For a list of numbers contained in a vector that we&#39;ll call x,
the average is simply defined as a sum of x divided by the length of x.
Here&#39;s the code that you use in R. And the standard deviation
is defined with the following formula.
It&#39;s the square root of the sum of the differences between the values
and the mean squared divided by the length.
You can think of this as the average distance
between the values and their average.
Let&#39;s compute the average and the standard deviation
for the male heights, which we will store in an object
called x using this code.
The pre-built function, mean and SD can be used here.
We don&#39;t have to type out the code that we showed before,
because these functions are so common that pre-built functions exist.
So the code would actually look like this.
We see that the average height is 69.31 inches
and the standard deviation is 3.61 inches.
So here is a plot of the smooth density of our male heights.
We&#39;re making no assumptions here, other than assuming it&#39;s somewhat smooth.
And then overlaid with a black curve is the normal distribution
that has average 69.31, and standard deviation 3.61.
Note how close those two are.
This is telling us that the normal distribution approximate
the distribution of our male heights.
Before we continue, let&#39;s introduce the concept of standard units.
For data that is approximately normal, it
is convenient to think in terms of standard units.
The standard unit of value tells us how many standard deviations away
from the average this value is.
Specifically for a value x, we define the standard unit
as z equals x minus the average divided by the standard deviation.
If you look back at the formula for the normal distribution,
you notice that what is being exponentiated is negative z squared.
The maximum of e to the minus z squared over 2
is when z equals 0, which explains why the maximum of the distribution
is at the average.
It also explains the symmetry, since negative z squared
is symmetric around 0.
To understand why standard units are useful,
notice that if we convert normally distributed data into standard units,
we can quickly know if for example, a person is about average height, that
would mean z equals 0.
A person that is tall would be z equals 2.
A person that is short would be z equals negative 2.
And extremely rare occurrences, say a 7 footer or something like that,
would have a z bigger than 3.
Or someone very short would have a z smaller negative 3.
Note that it does not matter what the original units are.
These rules apply to any data that is approximately normal.
In R, we can quickly obtain standard units using the function scale.
Type in this code.
Now back to our example.
To see how many men are within two standard deviations from the average,
now that we were already converted to standard units, all we have to do
is count the number of z&#39;s that are less than 2 and bigger than negative 2,
and then divide by the total.
So we take the mean of this quantity that you see here in the code,
and we see that the proportion is 0.951.
Note that it&#39;s about 95%, which is exactly
what the normal distribution predicts.
So it&#39;s quite useful.
If we can assume that the data is approximately normal,
at least for this interval, we can predict the proportion
without actually looking at the data.
We simply know that 95% of the data for normally
distributed data is between negative 2 and 2.
Now to further confirm that in fact the approximation is a good one,
we need to look at other intervals.
And for this, we will use quantile plots.