RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In the data visualization module,
we introduced the normal distribution as a useful approximation
to many naturally occurring distributions,
including that of height.
The cumulative distribution for the normal distribution
is defined by a mathematical formula, which in R can
be obtained with the function pnorm.
We say that a random quantity is normally distributed with average, avg,
and standard deviation, s, if its probability distribution
is defined by f of a equals pnorm a, average, s.
This is the code.
This is useful, because if we are willing to use the normal approximation
for say, height, we don&#39;t need the entire dataset
to answer questions such as, what is the probability that a randomly selected
student is taller than 70.5 inches.
We just need the average height and the standard deviation.
Then we can use this piece of code, 1 minus pnorm 70.5 mean of x, sd of x.
And that gives us the answer of 0.37.
The normal distribution is derived mathematically.
Apart from computing the average and the standard deviation,
we don&#39;t use data to define it.
Also the normal distribution is defined for continuous variables.
It is not described for discrete variables.
However, for practicing data scientists, pretty much everything we do
involves data, which is technically speaking discrete.
For example, we could consider our adult data categorical
with each specific height a unique category.
The probability distribution would then be
defined by the proportion of students reporting each of those unique heights.
Here is what a plot of that would look like.
This would be the distribution function for those categories.
So each reported height gets a probability
defined by the proportion of students reporting it.
Now while most students rounded up their height to the nearest inch,
others reported values with much more precision.
For example, student reported his height to be 69.6850393700787.
What is that about?
What&#39;s that very, very precise number?
Well, it turns out, that&#39;s 177 centimeters.
So the student converted it to inches, and copied and pasted the result
into the place where they had to report their heights.
The probability assigned to this height is about 0.001.
It&#39;s 1 in 708.
However, the probability for 70 inches is 0.12.
This is much higher than what was reported with this other value.
But does it really make sense to think that the probability of being exactly 70
inches is so much higher than the probability of being 69.68?
Clearly, it is much more useful for data analytic purposes
to treat this outcome as a continuous numeric variable.
But keeping in mind that very few people, perhaps none,
are exactly 70 inches.
But rather, that people rounded to the nearest inch.
With continuous distributions, the probability of a singular value
is not even defined.
For example, it does not make sense to ask
what is the probability that a normally distributed value is 70.
Instead, we define probabilities for intervals.
So we could ask instead, what is a probability that someone
is between 69.99 and 70.01.
In cases like height in which the data is rounded,
the normal approximation is particularly useful
if we deal with intervals that include exactly one round number.
So for example, the normal distribution is
useful for approximating the proportion of students
reporting between 69.5 and 70.5.
Here are three other examples.
Look at the numbers that are being reported.
This is using the data, the actual data, not the approximation.
Now look at what we get when we use the approximation.
We get almost the same values.
For these particular intervals, the normal approximation is quite useful.
However, the approximation is not that useful for other intervals.
For example, those that don&#39;t include an integer.
Here are two examples.
If we use these two intervals, again, this
is the data, look at the approximations now with the normal distribution.
They&#39;re not that good.
In general, we call this situation discretization.
Although the true height distribution is continuous,
the reported heights tend to be more common at discrete values,
in this case, due to rounding.
As long as we are aware of how to deal with this reality,
the normal approximation can still be a very useful tool.