RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In a previous video, we described
how, if a distribution is well approximated
by the normal distribution, we can have a very useful and short summary.
But to check if, in fact, it is a good approximation,
we can use quantile-quantile plots, or q-q plots.
We start by defining a series of proportion, for example, p equals 0.05,
0.10, 0.15, up to 0.95.
Once this is defined for each p, we determine the value q,
so that the proportion of the values in the data below q is p.
The q&#39;s are referred to as the quantiles.
To give a quick example, for the male heights
data that we showed in previous videos, we have that 50% of the data
is below 69.5 inches.
So this means that if p equals 0.5, then the q associated with that p is 69.5.
Now, we can make this computation for a series of p&#39;s.
If the quantiles for the data match the quantiles for the normal distribution,
then it must be because the data is approximated by a normal distribution.
To obtain the quantiles for the data, we can use the quantile function
in r like this.
So we&#39;re going to define an object called observe quantiles, and calculate
the quantiles for x at the series of values of p,
which is stored in the object p.
To obtain the theoretical normal distribution quantiles
with the corresponding average and standard deviation,
we use the qnorm function, like this.
We&#39;re going to find an object called theoretical quantiles.
To see if they match or not, we can plot them against each other,
and then draw an identity line to see if the points fall on the line.
We can do this using the plot function, like this.
Very simple piece of code produces this plot.
Note that the points fall almost on the line,
meaning that the normal approximation is a pretty good approximation.
Now, one final note.
This code becomes slightly simpler if we use standard units.
If we use standard units, we don&#39;t have to define
the mean and the standard deviation in the function qnorm.
So the code simplifies and looks like this.
Now, using the histogram, the density plots, and the q-q plots,
we have become convinced that the male height data is well approximated
with a normal distribution.
So in this case, we can report back to ET a very succinct summary.
Male heights follow a normal distribution,
with an average of 69.44 inches, and a standard deviation of 3.27 inches.
With this information, ET will have everything
he needs to know to describe, and know what to expect,
when he meets our male students.