RAFAEL IRIZARRY: In this short video, we define some terms that are commonly
used in exploratory data analysis.
Percentiles are special cases of quantiles that are commonly used.
The percentiles are the quantiles you obtain
when you define p as 0.01, 0.02, up to 0.99, 1%, 2%, 3%, et cetera.
This is why we call them percentiles.
We call, for example, the case of p equals 0.25 the 25th percentiles.
This gives us the number for which 25% other data is below.
The most famous percentile is the 50th, also known as the median.
Note that for the normal distribution, the median and the average
are the same.
But this is not generally the case.
Another special case that receives a name are the quartiles,
which are obtained when we set p to be 0.25, 0.50, and 0.75.