RAFAEL IRIZARRY: To introduce box plots, we will go back to the US murders data.
Suppose we want to summarize the murder rate distribution.
Using the data visualization techniques we have learned,
we notice that the normal approximation does not apply here.
We can see it in the histogram, we can see it in the QQ plot.
In this case, the histogram or smooth density plot,
would serve as a relatively succinct summary.
Now suppose you were trying to describe this data to someone
who is used to receiving just two numbers, the average
and the standard deviation.
In this case, that&#39;s not an appropriate summary,
but they still want something compact.
Here, John Tukey offers some advice.
Provide a five number summary composed of the range along with the quartiles,
25th, 50th, and 75th percentile.
Tukey further suggests that we ignore outliers when computing the range,
and instead plot these as independent points.
We provide a detailed explanation of outliers later.
Finally, he suggests that we plot this five number summary
as a box with whiskers like this.
The box is defined by the 25th and 75th percentiles,
and the whiskers are showing the range.
The distance between these two percentiles
is called the interquartile range.
The two points that are outliers according to Tukey&#39;s definition,
those are shown separately, and the median is shown with a horizontal line.
Today, we call these boxplots.
From just a simple plot, we know that the median is about 2.5,
that the distribution is not symmetric, and that the range
is 0 to 5 for the great majority of states with two exceptions, the two
outliers.
Boxplots are even more useful when we want to quickly compare
two or more distributions.
For example, here are the heights for men and women
from our self-reported heights from previous videos.
The plot immediately reveals that men are on average taller than women.
We also see that the standard deviation appears to be similar.