RAFAEL IRIZARRY: We start by covering some basic principles related to categorical data.
This subset of probability is referred to as discrete probability.
It will help us understand the probability theory
we will later introduce for numeric and continuous data, which is more
common in data science applications.
Discrete probability is more useful in card games
and we use these as examples.
The word probability is used in everyday language.
For example, Google's auto complete of, what are the chances of,
gives us getting pregnant, having twins, and rain tomorrow.
Answering questions about probability is often hard, if not impossible.
Here, we discuss a mathematical definition of probability
that does permit us to give precise answers to certain questions.
For example, if I have two red beads and three blue beads inside an urn
and I pick one at random, what is the probability of picking a red one?
Our intuition tells us that the answer is 2/5, or 40%.
A precise definition can be given by noting
that there are five possible outcomes of which two satisfy
the condition necessary for the event "pick a red bead."
Because each of the five outcomes has the same chance of occurring,
we conclude that the probability is 0.4 for red and 0.6 for blue.
A more tangible way to think about the probability of an event
is as a proportion of times the event occurs
when we repeat the experiment over and over independently and under the same
conditions.
Before we continue, let's introduce some notation.
We use the notation probability of A to denote the probability of an event A
happening.
We use the very general term event to refer
to things that can happen when something happens by chance.
For example, in our previous example, the event was picking a red bead.
In a political poll, in which we call 100 likely voters
at random, an example of an event is calling
48 Democrats and 52 Republicans.
In data science applications, we will often deal with continuous variables.
In these cases, events will often be things like,
is this person taller than 6 feet?
In this case, we write events in a more mathematical form.
For example, x greater than 6.
We'll see more of these examples later.
Here, we focus on categorical data and discrete probability.