RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Defining a distribution for categorical outcomes
is relatively straight forward.
We simply assign a probability to each category.
In cases that can be thought of as beads in an urn, for each bead type,
the proportion defines the distribution.
Another example comes from polling.
If you're are randomly calling likely voters from a population that
has 44% Democrat, 44% Republican, 10% undecided, and 2% green,
these proportions define the probability for each group.
For this example, the probability distribution
is simply these four proportions.
Again, categorical data makes it easy to define probability distributions.
However, later in applications that are more common in data science,
we will learn about probability distributions for continuous variables.
In this case, it'll get a little bit more complex.
But for now, we're going to stick to discrete probabilities
before we move on.