RAFAEL IRIZARRY: We say that two events are independent if the outcome of one
does not affect the other.
The classic example are coin tosses.
Every time we toss a fair coin, the probability of seeing heads
is 1/2 regardless of what previous tosses have revealed.
The same is true when we pick beads from an urn with replacement.
In the example we saw earlier, the probability of red
was .40 regardless of previous draws.
Many examples of events that are not independent come from card games.
When we deal the first card, the probability of getting, say,
a king is 1 in 13.
This is because there are 13 possibilities.
You can get an ace, a 2, a 3, a 4, et cetera, 10, jack, queen or king.
Now, if we deal a king for the first card and I don&#39;t replace it,
then the problem of getting a king in the second card
is less because there are only three kings left.
The probability is 3 out of not 52--
because we already dealt one card-- but out of 51.
These events are, therefore, not independent.
The first outcome affects the second.
To see an extreme case of non-independent events,
consider an example of drawing five beads at random
without replacement from an urn.
Three are blue, two are red.
I&#39;m going to generate data like this using the sample function
and assign it to x.
You can&#39;t see the outcomes.
Now, if I ask you to guess the color of the first bead, what do you guess?
Since there&#39;s more blue beads, there&#39;s actually a 0.6 chance of seeing blue.
That&#39;s probably what you guess.
But now, I&#39;m going to show you the outcomes of the other four.
The second, third, fourth and fifth outcomes you can see here.
You can see that the three blue beads have already come out.
This affects the probability of the first.
They are not independent.
So would you still guess blue?
Of course not.
Now, you know that the probability of red is 1.
These events are not independent.
The probabilities change once you see the other outcomes.
When events are not independent, conditional probabilities
are useful and necessary to make correct calculations.
We already saw an example of a conditional probability.
We computed the probability that a second dealt card is
a king given that the first was a king.
In probability, we use the following notation.
We use this dash like this as a shorthand
for given that or conditional on.
These are synonyms.
Note that, when two events, say A and B, are independent,
we have the following equation.
The probability of A given B is equal to the probability of A.
It doesn&#39;t matter what B is.
The probability A is unchanged.
This is the mathematical way of saying it.
And in fact, this can be considered the mathematical definition
of independence.
All right now.
If we want to know the probability of two events, say A and B, occurring,
we can use the multiplication rule.
So the probability of A and B is equal to the probability of A multiplied
by the probability of B given that A already happened.
Let&#39;s use blackjack as an example.
In blackjack, you get assigned two random cards without replacement.
Then, you can ask for more.
The goal is to get closer to 21 than the dealer without going over.
Face cards are worth 10 points.
So is the 10 card.
That&#39;s worth 10 points, too.
And aces are worth either 11 or 1.
So if you get an ace and a face card, you win automatically.
So, in blackjack, to calculate the chances of getting 21
in the following way, first we get an ace
and then we get a face card or a 10, we compute the problem of the first
being an ace and then multiply by the probability of a face card
or a 10 given that the first card was an ace.
This calculation is 1/13--
chance of getting an ace--
times the chance of getting a card with value 10
given that we already saw an ace, which is 16 out of 51.
We&#39;ve already taken one card out.
This is approximately 2%.
The multiplicative rule also applies to more than two events.
We can use induction to expand for more than two.
So the probability of A and B and C is equal to the probability of A times
the probability of B given that A happened times the probability of C
that A and b happened.
When we have independent events, the multiplication rule becomes simpler.
We simply multiply the three probabilities.
But we have to be very careful when we use a multiplicative rule in practice.
We&#39;re assuming independence, and this can
result in very different and incorrect probability calculations
when we don&#39;t actually have independence.
This could have dire consequences, for example, in a trial
if an expert doesn&#39;t really know the multiplication rule and how to use it.
So let&#39;s use an example.
This is loosely based on something that actually happened.
Imagine a court case in which the suspect was described
to have a mustache and a beard, and the prosecution brings in an expert
to argue that, because 1 in 10 men have beards and 1 in 5 men
has mustaches, using the multiplication rule, this means that only 2% of men
have both beards and mustaches--
1/10 times 1/5.
2% is a pretty unlikely event.
However, to multiply like this, we need to assume independence.
And in this case, it&#39;s clearly not true.
The conditional probability of a man having a mustache conditional on them
having a beard is quite high.
It&#39;s about 95%.
So the correct calculation actually gives us a much higher probability.
It&#39;s 9%.
So there&#39;s definitely reasonable doubt.