RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Before we continue, let&#39;s
make an important clarification related to the practical problem of forecasting
the election.
If a poll is conducted 4 months before the election,
it is estimating the p for that moment, not for election day.
But, note that the p for election night might
be different since people&#39;s opinions fluctuate through time.
The polls provided the night before the election tend to be the most accurate
since opinions don&#39;t change that much in a couple of days.
However, forecasters try to build tools that model how opinions
vary across time and try to predict the election day
result, taking into consideration the fact that opinions fluctuate.
We&#39;ll describe some approaches for doing this in a later section.