RAFAEL IRIZARRY: To understand how good our estimate is,
we'll describe the statistical properties of the random variable we
just defined, the sample proportion.
Note that, if we multiply by N, N times X-bar is a sum of independent draws,
so the rules we covered in the probability module apply.
Using what we have learned, the expected value of the sum N times X-bar
is N times the average of the urn, p.
So, dividing by the nonrandom constant N gives us
that the expected value of the average X-bar is p.
We can write it using our mathematical notation like this.
We also can use what we learned to figure out the standard error.
We know that the standard error of the sum is square root of N
times the standard deviation of the values in the urn.
Can we compute the standard error of the urn?
We learned a formula that tells us that it's
1 minus 0 times the square of p times 1 minus p,
which is the square root of p times 1 minus p.
Because we are dividing by the sum, N, we
arrive at the following formula for the standard error of the average.
The standard error of the average is square root of p times 1 minus p
divided by the square root of N.
This result reveals the power of polls.
The expected value of the sample proportion, X-bar,
is the parameter of interest, p.
And we can make the standard error as small
as we want by increasing the sample size, N. The law of large numbers
tells us that, with a large enough poll, our estimate converges to p.
If we take a large enough poll to make our standard error, say, about 0.01,
we'll be quite certain about who will win.
But how large does a poll have to be for the standard error to be this small?
One problem is that we do not know p, so we can't actually
compute the standard error.
For illustrative purposes, let's assume that p is 0.51
and make a plot of the standard error versus the sample size N. Here it is.
You can see that obviously it's dropping.
From the plot, we also see that we would need a poll of over 10,000 people
to get the standard error as low as we want it to be.
We rarely see polls of this size due, in part, to costs.
We'll give other reasons later.
From the RealClearPolitics table we saw earlier,
we learned that the sample sizes in opinion polls range from 500 to 3,500.
For a sample size of 1,000, if we set p to be 0.51,
the standard error is about 0.015, or 1.5 percentage points.
So even with large polls, for close elections,
X-bar can lead us astray if we don't realize it's a random variable.
But, we can actually say more about how close we can get to the parameter p.
We'll do that in the next video.