RAFAEL IRIZARRY: We started this series of videos
by asking to describe heights of students to ET.
However, we&#39;ve only described male heights.
We did this with just two numbers.
So to give a full summary of heights, we still have to summarize female heights.
We expect that they will follow a normal distribution, just like the men.
However, exploratory plots reveal that the approximation is not as useful.
We can see it in the density plot or the q-q plot.
We see something that we did not see for males.
The density plot has a second bump around 67.
Looks like a little shoulder.
Also the q-q plot shows that the highest points tend to be taller than expected
for the normal distribution.
So when reporting back to ET, we might need
to provide a histogram rather than just the average and the standard deviation
for the female heights.
More importantly, we have noticed something that we didn&#39;t expect to see.
This reminds us of a quote from Tukey, &quot;The greatest value of a picture
is when it forces us to notice what we never expected to see.&quot;
If we look at other female height distributions from other sources,
other than our self-reported heights, we do
find that they are well approximated for the normal distribution.
So why do we see a second hump in our data?
Why do we see so many outliers, so many taller than expected women?
Is our class a requirement for the female basketball team?
Are small proportions of females claiming to be taller than they are?
Another, perhaps more likely explanation,
is that in the form students used to enter their heights,
the internet form, female was the default sex,
and some males may have entered their heights,
but they forgot to change the sex variable.
In this case, in our data set, some of the values that are supposedly
from females are actually males.
In any case, this is a good example of how
data visualization has helped us discover a potential flaw in our data.