RAFAEL IRIZARRY: Looking at the numbers and character strings
at the final dataset is rarely useful.
To convince yourself, print and stare at the US murders data table.
You can do this with this code.
What do you learn from staring at this table?
How quickly can you determine which states have the largest populations?
Which states have the smallest?
How large is a typical state?
Is there a relationship between population size and total murders?
How do the murder rates vary across regions of the country?
For most human brains, it is quite difficult
to extract this information just from looking at the numbers.
In contrast, the answer to all of these questions
are readily available from examining this plot.
We are reminded of the saying, &quot;A picture is worth a thousand words.&quot;
Data visualization provides a powerful way
to communicate a data driven finding.
In some cases, the visualization is so convincing that no follow up analysis
is required.
The growing availability of informative data sets and software tools
has lead to increased reliance on data visualization
across many industries, academia, and government.
A visible example are news organizations that are increasingly
embracing data journalism and including effective info-graphics
and charts as part of their reporting.
A particularly effective example is a Wall Street Journal article
showing data related to the impact of vaccines
on battling infectious diseases.
One of the graphs shows measles cases by US state
through the years with a vertical line demonstrating
when the vaccine was introduced.
Another striking example comes from the New York Times.
This article showed data on scores from the New York City regents exam.
These scores are collected for several reasons,
including to determine if a student graduates from high school.
In New York City, you need a 65 to pass.
The distribution of the test scores forces
us to notice something somewhat problematic.
The most common test score is the minimum passing grade.
With very few just below that value.
This unexpected result is consistent with students
close to passing having their scores bumped up.
This is an example of how data visualization can
lead to discoveries which would otherwise
be missed if we simply subject that data to a battery of data analysis, tools,
or procedures.
Data visualization is the strongest tool of what
we call exploratory data analysis.
John Tukey, considered the father of exploratory data analysis
once said, the greatest value of a picture
is when it forces us to notice what we never expected to see.
We note that many widely used data analysis
tools were initiated by discoveries made with exploratory data analysis.
Exploratory data analysis is perhaps the most important part of data analysis,
yet it is often overlooked.
Data visualization is also now pervasive and philanthropic
in educational organizations.
One example comes from GAPminder and the talks, New Insights on Poverty
and the Best Stats You&#39;ve Ever Seen, Hans Roslings
forced us to notice the unexpected with a series of plots
related to world health and economics.
In his videos, he used animated graphs to show us how the world was changing,
and how old narratives are no longer true.
It is also important to note that mistakes, biases, systematic errors,
and other unexpected problems often lead to data
that should be handled with care.
Failure to discover these problems often leads to flawed analyses
and false discoveries.
As an example, consider that measurement devices sometimes fail
and that most data analysis procedures are not designed to detect these yet.
These data analysis procedures will still give you an answer.
The fact that it can be hard or impossible to notice an error just
from the reported results makes data visualization particularly important.
In this course, we will learn the basics of data visualization
and exploratory data analysis.
We will use motivating examples.
We will use the ggplot2 package to code.
To learn the basics, we will start with a somewhat artificial example, heights
reported by students.
Then we will cover two of the examples we mentioned,
world health and economics, and infectious diseases
trends in the United States.
Note that there&#39;s much more to data visualization that
will be covered here.
But you will get a very good introduction to the topic.