[KEYBOARD TYPING]
RAFAEL IRIZARRY: You may have noticed that numerical data is often
summarized with an average value.
For example, the quality of a high school is sometimes
summarized with one number--
the average score in a standardized test.
Occasionally, a second number is reported
as well-- the standard deviation.
So, for example, you might read a report stating that scores at this high school
were 680 plus or minus 50.
The last number is the standard deviation.
Note that the report has summarized an entire vector of scores
with just two numbers.
Is this appropriate?
Is there any important piece of information
we&#39;re missing by only looking at this summary rather than the entire list?
It turns out that in some cases, these two numbers
are pretty much all we need to understand the data.
Data visualization techniques will help us determine when
this two-number summary is appropriate.
These same techniques will serve as alternatives for when
these two numbers are not enough.
Our first data visualization building block
is learning to summarize lists of factors or numeric vectors.
The most basic statistical summary of a list of objects or numbers
is its distribution.
Once a vector has been summarized as a distribution,
there are several data visualization techniques to effectively relay
this information.