RAFAEL IRIZARRY: An important first step in deciding how to visualize data
is to know what type of data it is.
We will be working with two types of variables-- categoricals
and numericals.
Each can be divided into two further groups.
Categoricals can be divided into ordinals and non-ordinals.
And numerical variables can be divided into discrete or continuous.
Variables that are defined by a small number of groups
we call categorical data.
Two simple examples are sex, male or female, or regions of the states
that we looked at in the first course--
Northeast, South, Central, West.
Some categorical data can be ordered.
For example, spiciness can be mild, medium, or hot.
Even if they are not numbers per se, they can still be ordered.
In statistics textbooks they sometimes refer to these as ordinal data.
The other data type are numericals.
Examples that we have seen or will see are population sizes, murder rates,
and heights.
We can further divide numerical data into continuous and discrete.
Continuous variables are those that can take any value such as heights
if measured with enough precision.
For example, a pair of twins maybe 68.12 inches and 68.11 inches respectively.
Counts such as population sizes are discrete
because they have to be round numbers.
Note that discrete numeric data can be considered ordinal.
An example are heights rounded to the nearest inch.
Although this is technically true, we usually
reserve the term &quot;ordinal data&quot; for variables
belonging to a small number of different groups
with each group having many members.
In contrast, when we have many groups with few cases in each group,
we typically refer to this as discrete numerical variables.
So for example, the number of packs of cigarettes a person smokes a day
rounded to the closest pack-- so 0, 1, or 2--
would be considered ordinal.
While the number of cigarettes that we smoke--
0, 1, 2, 3 up to maybe 36--
would be considered a numerical variable.
But indeed, these examples can be considered both
when it comes to data visualization.
Now that we&#39;ve learned about the different data types,
we&#39;re ready to learn about data visualization techniques.